Scenario Based questions:

Will the reducer work or not if you use “Limit 1” in any HiveQL query?
If we use a simple select * query then the reducer will not work as it will create a fetch task only.
But if we use other queries such as group by or other aggregations then the reducer will work.

Suppose I have installed Apache Hive on top of my Hadoop cluster using default metastore configuration. Then, what will happen if we have multiple clients trying to access Hive at the same time? 
As the default metastore configuration in hive uses derby db only one connection is supported at a time.If we try to access using multiple clients it will give error.If we want multiple concurrent clients we have to use a standalone metastore, i.e. Local or remote metastore configuration in Apache Hive.

Suppose, I create a table that contains details of all the transactions done by the customers: CREATE TABLE transaction_details (cust_id INT, amount FLOAT, month STRING, country STRING) ROW FORMAT DELIMITED FIELDS TERMINATED BY ‘,’ ;
Now, after inserting 50,000 records in this table, I want to know the total revenue generated for each month. But, Hive is taking too much time in processing this query. How will you solve this problem and list the steps that I will be taking in order to do so?
As hive is taking too much time in processing this query we can partition the table transaction_details on month column so now when query runs it only loads the data from the partitions and does not scan the full data.
Steps to Partition the table: 
1.CREATE TABLE transaction_details_part
(cust_id INT, 
amount FLOAT, 
country STRING)
 PARTITIONED BY (month STRING) 
ROW FORMAT DELIMITED 
FIELDS TERMINATED BY ‘,’ ;
2.SET hive.exec.dynamic.partition = true;
 SET hive.exec.dynamic.partition.mode = nonstrict;
3.Load the data into partitioned table INSERT OVERWRITE TABLE transaction_details_part PARTITION (month) SELECT cust_id, amount, country, month FROM transaction_details;

How can you add a new partition for the month December in the above partitioned table?
ALTER TABLE transaction_details_part ADD PARTITION (month=’Dec’) LOCATION ‘/transaction_details;

I am inserting data into a table based on partitions dynamically. But, I received an error – FAILED ERROR IN SEMANTIC ANALYSIS: Dynamic partition strict mode requires at least one static partition column. How will you remove this error?
SET hive.exec.dynamic.partition = true;
SET hive.exec.dynamic.partition.mode = nonstrict;

Suppose, I have a CSV file – ‘sample.csv’ present in ‘/temp’ directory with the following entries:
id first_name last_name email gender ip_address
How will you consume this CSV file into the Hive warehouse using built-in SerDe?
CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE sample
 (id int, 
first_name string,
 last_name string,
 email string,
 gender string,
 ip_address string) 
ROW FORMAT SERDE ‘org.apache.hadoop.hive.serde2.OpenCSVSerde’
 STORED AS TEXTFILE LOCATION ‘/temp’;

Suppose, I have a lot of small CSV files present in the input directory in HDFS and I want to create a single Hive table corresponding to these files. The data in these files are in the format: {id, name, e-mail, country}. Now, as we know, Hadoop performance degrades when we use lots of small files.
So, how will you solve this problem where we want to create a single Hive table for lots of small files without degrading the performance of the system?
One can use the SequenceFile format which will group these small files together to form a single sequence file. The steps that will be followed in doing so are as follows: We need to create a sequence file to resolve this issue.
Steps to create a sequence file 
● Create a temporary table:
 CREATE TABLE temp ( id INT, name STRING, email STRING, country STRING) DELIMITED TERMINATED BY ‘,’ STORED AS TEXTFILE;
● Load the data into temp: LOAD DATA INPATH ‘/input’ INTO TABLE temp; 
● Create a table that will store data in SequenceFile format: CREATE TABLE seq (id INT, name STRING, email STRING, country STRING) ROW FORMAT DELIMITED FIELDS  TERMINATED BY ‘,’ STORED AS SEQUENCEFILE; 
● Load the data from the temporary table into the seq table: INSERT OVERWRITE TABLE seq SELECT * FROM temp;

LOAD DATA LOCAL INPATH ‘Home/country/state/’ OVERWRITE INTO TABLE address; The following statement failed to execute. What can be the cause?
As we are loading data from local, the path should contain a file path not a directory path.
Eg: LOAD DATA LOCAL INPATH ‘Home/country/state/file_name.txt’ OVERWRITE INTO TABLE address;


